hello everybody and welcome back to
active inference insights today I am
honored to be speaking with Professor
Mark SS Professor SS is a
neuropsychologist and psychoanalyst best
known for his discovery of the full
brain mechanisms underlying dreams and
his integration of psychoanalytic
theories with modern Neuroscience more
recently he's been focusing on active
inference and what it might bring to
bear on the hardest problem of them all
Consciousness mark thank you so much for
joining me it's a yeah as I said in the
introduction it's a real honor and
privilege it's it's great to be here
Darius thanks very much so yeah I mean
you have been in the field of cognitive
Neuroscience for many decades but I
guess have only recently in the last 10
years or so have really taken an
interest in in active inference and
seeing you know as many people have I
think when I I read your book um The
Hidden Spring which is a wonderful read
and I think what I really liked about it
I've been looking I'm very interested in
the hard problem and trying to kind of
see different perspectives with which we
can take to to approach the hard problem
and I've been looking for what I've been
calling the synthetic a priori of
Consciousness and what I mean by that is
can we have a can we determine a
function of cognition that needs to be
conscious a priori so for example you
could say attention well I can imagine
offline attention I'm just sort of
pinging around without it being online
and I thought you got very close and I I
will not say determin you know I will
not say in a determined fashion because
David Charmers will shs at me but I
think you got very close with this
notion that affect is a good candidate
for what I would call the synthetic a
prior of Consciousness now affect is can
be seen as a kind of loose term so I
think where we might want to start is
just if you could give a kind of brief
definition of what you mean by affect
because obviously um maybe what you and
yach panp in basic emotion Theory think
is a might differ from a constructionist
account of aect and so on so maybe if we
could just start laying down what affect
is before we get to
Consciousness thank you um yes that's a
good uh point to start with because as
you say different people do mean
different things by that term um so what
I mean by affect is first and not not
foremost but first that it is valanced
in other words there's a goodness and
Badness um to affect
and um appropo of your opening remarks
about a um aiori synthetic function uh
the I think I should mention that the
goodness and Badness of affect um is it
applies only to the subject of the
affect so it's good from my point of
view or bad from my point of view it
doesn't mean that it is objectively or
universally good or bad so an affective
state uh is a valanced state it has
goodness and Badness the second um and
perhaps this is the uh when I said I
don't want to say first and foremost
veilance because perhaps this is the
foremost
characteristic is that it is qualified
by which I mean uh it has a specific uh
differentiated quality there are there
are different affects so although all
affects share the the um property of
veilance of goodness or Badness um each
affect has its own unique quality um I
don't mean to say that they aren't
intermediate forms of affect but what I
mean is that the that the feeling of
hunger uh is qualitatively different
from the feeling of thirst is
qualitatively different from the feeling
of sleepiness and so on and uh this is
important um
because you you you you can't you can't
say um I have uh currently six out of 10
of sleepiness and six out of 10 of
thirst therefore um I have uh 12 out of
20 of total bily need and all I need to
be is sleep uh if you if you did that
you would reduce the the the the common
uh denominator uh the the the continuous
variable of need but you would die uh
that is because uh sleepiness and thirst
are not the same thing they are
qualitatively different they are
categorical variables so so that's for
me uh the essential features of affect
that they valanced um which which
implies they're subjective their
veillance is subjective uh and they are
categorical uh qualitatively
differentiated uh
States okay that's really useful so I
think before we get into the qualitative
distinctions because I you know uh
people may have seen your debates with
Lisa Felman Barrett um and how deep that
distinction runs was kind of a sticking
point in your in your conversations
before we go there we don't even
necessarily need to go there I think the
really interesting point there is that
good or Badness is only good or Badness
for a subject I've been thinking about
this in terms of relevance or
prioritization that whatever enters into
the space of Consciousness is always
prioritized or relevant to the
uh to the agent now I think there's a
second question that I will come to
about are we not putting the C for the
horse by H inferring the presence of an
agent for whom something is good or bad
but before I go there folding in
something like salience relevance or
priority is that uh built into the
goodness or Badness of the signal of the
phenomenal state or is it or does it
necessarily underly or underwrite that
phenomenal
State um the way I look on it is that
the the underlying category is a
category of need uh you do not feel all
your needs so for example your need for
energy resources um is met by your
constantly burning up the uh glucose uh
deposited in your ad
tissues but you don't feel anything um
when that um need is prioritized you
then feel hunger um so the
prioritization and the becoming
conscious of the need are I think
intimately bound up with each
other and so what therefore does that
say for this kind of synthetic aior of
Consciousness in so far as if relevance
or salience or priority whatever you
want to say
is it it's difficult to imagine being
conscious of something which is not in
some way Salient to
you does that put the that notion of
salience uh which we could you know I've
been proposing that Consciousness might
be something like a relevance filter or
a salience filter would that make that
function that relevance function more
akin to this synthetic aior of
Consciousness than affect per se
I think that uh the answer to that is
bound up with uh what do we mean when we
say we we are prioritizing one need over
another it's not it's not the
prioritization is not an end in itself
it's a prioritization for Action uh you
can't you can't do everything uh at once
um in terms of um this prioritization uh
uh uh imperative and I'll explain what I
mean by that uh and has everything to do
with when you say an aoi synthetic
function um it has everything to do with
what function we are talking about so
what I'm saying is that that function is
not merely the function of need or the
registration of a need uh it's the
feeling of the need and what
functionality is added by the feeling of
the need has everything to do with the
action bottleneck that I was talking
about the prioritized need is felt
so that you can monitor how well or
badly you're doing uh in your attempts
to meet that need the nonprioritized
needs are relegated to automaticity the
actions that you perform in relation to
the nonprioritized needs do not have to
be felt because uh they are being met or
at least attempts are being made to meet
them outside of Consciousness by
existing uh fixed um policies the
prioritized need which is felt uh the
the function of the feeling is precisely
because you're in a state of uncertainty
um the the the automaticity uh doesn't
cut it automaticity is dangerous uh
because you don't know what to do so
you're feeling your way through a novel
situation or through an unpredicted
situation and um the the the feeling
tells you whether what you're currently
doing the policy you're currently
following whether it's working or not so
it underwrites Choice uh it underwrites
the possibility uh of changing your mind
on the Fly um and then of course
learning from the experience which which
which results in the laying down of new
predictions which may in future uh be
executed unconsciously it's while you
it's sort of predictive work in
progress I suppose is a is a good way um
of describing it and I want to um make
explicit what I in something in what
I've just said when I said that this
underwrites Choice um it means that it
underwrites voluntary action so this is
the mechanistic difference in my view
between voluntary and automatic or
autonomic
action so yeah okay that's that's
interesting there are some things that I
think we can fold in from an active
inference perspective because um you
were talking you were talking about
almost metacognitive monitoring of how
well you're doing at minimizing free
energy and that actually has been
fleshed out in in active inference as a
COR jofy and Corelli paper all the way
back in 2013 but recently people have
been talking about um era Dynamics which
is this awareness of how well you're
doing at minimizing free energy over a
span of time and they have Associated
that with
veilance my question here is more
therefore philosophical so it's not
really pulling that in aart um although
there might be some people who who would
encourage me to do do so but rather why
couldn't that uh monitoring be done
offline so what is it about and this
really gets to the heart of this notion
of a synthetic priority of Consciousness
I can imagine in some sense a robot in
some fault experiment who was able to
offline attribute goodness or Badness to
their experience and use that in a
functional manner to guide their
expected free energy calculations let's
say what is there something critical to
experience per se which makes it
adaptive um for these free energy
minimizing systems and their
metacognitive capacities to track their
ability to minimize free energy yes I
believe that there is before I um
explain why I just want to flag maybe
for later discussion so I don't I don't
divert us from the question that you're
the line of questioning that you're
currently following that I'm not so sure
that I would describe the mechanism that
um I just articulated as a
metacognitive uh mechanism I I think
there's a difference between um the
feeling um and what the feeling is about
in other words there's a difference
between uh the the the raw feeling which
is the registering uh of what's
happening to your in in the terms that
you were just using uh to your free
energy and um you're cognizing
uh representing to use another language
um what uh in in the context within
which I'm feeling this what is causing
me to feel this so sure I yeah I
certainly I certainly agree with that
yeah I didn't mean to say in terms of
metacognitive purely this notion that it
can be done in some pre-reflexive
non-conceptual non-representational
manner purely this notion that there is
at least embedded in phenomenal space
some self referential but it could be
very low level like lived experience I
am doing well I am doing badly but it
doesn't have to be a higher order
narrative um I doing well I'm doing
badly okay good now um to your question
you ask why can't this function that
I've just described uh as the mechanism
of feeling uh you're asking why can't it
go on in the dark uh why why why is it
why is it necessary for it to be felt so
let me if you'll just bear with me for a
for a couple of minutes let me unpack
the mechanism in in slightly more
pedantic detail um we're talking about a
self-organizing system uh which is which
is intrinsically imbued uh with the
um the the um function that it must
continue what it does uh must uh
maximize its chances of continuing to
exist so that's a sort of pre that's a
starting point of of of any complex
dynamical self-organizing system so
there is a kind of intrinsic I don't say
kind of there is an intrinsic
intentionality in such a system it's
trying to achieve something I don't mean
it's metacognitively trying to achieve
something I just mean it has it has a
goal
directedness let me let me put it that
way um now
it's I then said that um the monitoring
of how well or badly I'm doing uh this
this can this veilance function um
that's what veilance is because it's
just to the extent that what I'm doing
um is moving me out of my viable bounds
is making me less likely to survive to
and vice versa you know when it's moving
me back towards my viable bonds that
just is good or bad for the system
the but again I need to emphasize the
point that I emphasized earlier it just
is good or bad for the
system in in in uh Nagel's sense it's
it's it's good for the system and good
to the system you know so it's not it's
not good or bad in any objective sense
it's good or bad only in a subjective
sense now you're saying why can't that
sort of monitoring uh be done um in the
dark I'm saying it can that's why I made
the point earlier about the difference
between the continuous variable of total
need or total free energy um and the
categorical variable um of which which
need am I talking about here categorical
variables just are distinguished
qualitatively as I said earlier thirst
and sleepiness just are not the same
thing uh so they are categorical
variables uh that means they're
qualitatively different so what I've
just described is something which
mechanistically is a felt state I'm
saying I'm saying from the point of view
of the system there is an an existential
uh variable uh called veilance in other
words this this is uh good or bad for me
uh for my continued existence whether or
not this is metacognitively reflected it
doesn't matter there is this thing which
just is good or bad and just is
subjective and it just is qualitatively
differentiated so if you're saying that
there's a certain function U that the
system has uh which is intrinsically
subjective intrinsically valanced um and
intrinsically qualitatively
distinguished I'm saying that is a
feeling so if you say say how can that
go on in the dark I would say what do
you mean
uh this intrinsically is something that
is felt that's the me a mechanistic
description of what a feeling is and I
think that the crucial step um that uh
needs to be um uh identified there um is
that is it justifiable to take the point
of view of the system in other words
what is it that justifies one uh to take
the Viewpoint of the system and I hope
you can see in what I
said the in the intrinsically subjective
nature of the things that I was talking
about there that justifies us the self
of the system justifies Us in taking the
subjective point of view of the system
and if you do that from a subjective
point of view the mechanism I've just
described um just is a feeling that's
what we mean by a feeling so um I I I I
hope I've been plain
clear enough you have well you have been
for me I mean I'm familiar with these
arguments of sort of intrinsic
intentionality I mean as you know they
go all the way back to haiger and this
notion of taking a stance on your own
being and the idea that it's kind of
open-ended we are naturally as you say
directed towards this kind of open-ended
Futurity and that's gets fleshed out in
you know I've recently just finished
Evan Thompson's mind in life and he is
wonderfully clear on that about this
idea of kind of we make we the unel
comes out of our own stance that we take
upon the world I guess I still have a
kind of residual Charmers
skepticism which is does and I think
therefore it's necessary to get kind of
clear on the axioms that you're taking
here does taking an intentional stance
on your own being require Consciousness
maybe intent well intentional is
actually not necessarily the wrong word
here but I mean can you have a
self-organizing complex dynamical system
and I think there's an interesting point
here about the imperative but I'll come
back to that but can you have a complex
self organizing system which is
autopoetic in the sense it it is
intended towards its own um self
persistence which need not be conscious
or at least conscious in the way that we
think of a conscious as subjectively
conscious I can almost imagine that you
have a nonsubjective
Consciousness I.E an objective
Consciousness if one could imagine and
such a thing which might in some
ways uh suit that self-organizing
process because it gets rid of bias and
uh overfitting your data and
confirmation bias and all this other
stuff I recognize we've gone slightly
off the beat and track here but I'm just
wondering whether there's like one thing
that I'm missing maybe it's an axiom or
maybe it's an argument I'm not sure
about exactly why autopoetic self
organization entails subjectivity per
se um well well let me start um with an
appeal to Authority which is not a good
thing uh and then uh let me add a um
semantic point which is not a good thing
and then I'll I'll answer your question
properly sure the appeal to Authority I
have to say um I was very pleased that
Tom Nagel wrote a commentary on my book
in the journal yeah he wrote it in the
Journal of Consciousness studies um
and there he he said in in in relation
to exactly the question you've just
asked that he thinks that it's it's a
non
nonstarter the idea of an affective
zombie so he accepts that it cannot be
an affective zombie this this is a this
is a
nonsecretor um but that's an appeal to
Authority I'm just saying no less a
person the nature of subjectivity uh he
he says he he accepts that there cannot
be an an affective zombie in other words
there cannot be a system equipped with
the functionality that I've just
described that is a zombie because if it
were a zombie it wouldn't have the
functionality I've described but that's
just an appeal to Authority then there's
the semantic Point um I want to make
clear that I'm talking about feeling
okay and you asked me earlier about
affect and you said different people use
the word in different ways and they mean
different things by it um I Hope from my
description of how what I mean by the
word you can see why I use it
synonymously with feeling um I like to
use the word feeling when I'm discussing
the issues that you're raising because
it just is an oxymoron to speak of a
feeling that you don't feel uh there's
it's not a feeling if you don't feel it
uh and and so the thing denoted by that
word um is the thing I'm talking about
now I said already that I accept that
that's just a semantic point and you
know but it it it leads to something
more than a semantic point when I say
the thing I'm talking about is the thing
denoted by the word feeling therefore
the thing I'm talking about cannot be
unfelt because uh that's the thing I'm
talking about the thing I'm talking
about is the thing that we call feeling
now that leads me to the substantive
answer to your question I really do
believe that
this this question as you formulated it
um I I I recognize of course as you
formulated it derived from or with um
with reference to David chs's
formulation of it um I don't think this
question would ever have Arisen if it
wasn't for the fact that uh we were
using as at the time that Charmers wrote
his famous paper and the book that
followed it um and formulated this term
the hard problem of Consciousness um we
were using as our model example of
Consciousness visual
Consciousness uh um This was um perhaps
uh inevitable because Consciousness is
dominated by Vision uh and uh it was
perhaps um because Francis Crick used it
as his model example in his book uh the
the the um uh what was it called the
astonishing hypothesis which came out
one year before uh charm's paper um the
thing is that I think that was the wrong
place to start that all of those
questions arise only because vision is
not an intrinsically conscious function
uh even the highest of visual um
functionality uh in other words uniquely
human cortical um visual functions like
reading with comprehension can be done
without Consciousness so the question
why doesn't all this information
processing go on in the dark without any
inner field which is to quote exactly
the the phraseology that Charmers used I
think that that's a legitimate question
and I can see why the puzzlement arises
because you can do exactly the same
thing without Consciousness so you know
like reading with comprehension why on
Earth do you ever why does there have to
be something it is like to read if the
exact same thing can done without there
being something it's like to do it now
you then once you've got this puzzlement
then somebody like you a reader of
Charmers comes to my argument and says
well why is it inconceivable that this
thing couldn't be done by an affective
zombie and I'm saying well that's a
silly question because look at what I've
just told you you know I've told you
what the function is I've told you that
it is intrinsically subjective it's
intrinsically existential it's
intrinsically veence uh and it's
qualitatively distinguished and if you
describe such a
mechanism which is necessarily
registered by the system then you're
describing a feeling so what do you mean
it could be not felt it wouldn't be a
feeling if it was not felt and I've told
you what the feeling does you know and
yeah I guess I guess I need to be a
little bit more philosophically robuster
and it's come to mind here that one can
take charma's claims and and that 95
paper and the book in multiple ways so
one is why um couldn't this
functionality be done in the dark and I
take and I agree actually that
feeling a prior in and of itself by
definition has to be felt so that's
something that you can have which needs
to be felt so that that notion of in the
darkness doesn't really stand when it
comes to
affect the another the other part of
David charma's argument is how do neural
processes give r rise to subjective
states to what it feels like to be me or
you and I guess that is a different
direction which I presume you probably
don't think there is an answer to and I
guess what that leads me back to is when
I'm talking about the synthetic a prior
of Consciousness sure feeling gets us
there I guess what I was saying is if we
go if we have the sort of view from
nowhere we can go back all the way to
the evolutionary start and let's say we
did start as non-conscious beings why
was it functionally adaptive for human
beings to develop feelings in the first
place right if this metacognitive
non-representational uh self-referential
process what it became imbued with
feeling not I'm not going to ask how
that happened because no one knows but I
guess the question here is why did that
happen and that's when I say well
couldn't couldn't have happened in the
dark sure feelings themselves can't
happen in the dark per se but the
function that feelings fulfill namely
this monitoring process why why did that
have to evolve so as to contain qualia
subjectivity and and so on that's the
kind of Crux of the question I
guess um I think you're I think either
you're asking three questions or I've
got three answers uh to your question so
I'm so I'm not so okay so I don't okay I
think there's actually only one here one
okay so I'm not fussed about how I'm
gonna lose my train of thought I'm an
old go go go go go go please me go go go
so um if I haven't already lost it um ah
yeah what I want to say first of all is
the um Mary uh the visual
neuroscientist um if if if she were an
affective neuroscientist uh if she were
to describe the to know everything there
is to know about the mechanism of
feeling it would necessarily predict
that it feels like something and and she
would know something about what it is
like to have a feeling from the
mechanistic account of it um that's
that's that's the the first thing that
you were saying in your question brought
that answer to my mind but I think you
said you concede that point uh I'm not
uninterested I'm uninterested I well now
I'm interested but I was uninterested in
the how and I'm and I'll give you the
feelings need to be felt I guess my
question is
evolutionarily why does the function of
feeling need to be felt yes so um that
leads to or or that to get to that I've
got to go via a second thing that I I
heard you saying which is um you know
how does the physiological process cause
the subjective feeling State and there I
have to make clear that I am a dual
aspect monist um I'm you may want to
explain what that is for the audience
yes I I I will um I'll put it uh very
simply uh when I wake up in the morning
uh before I open my eyes I experience my
existence I think to myself I am Mark
Psalms thank God I'm still alive that's
my mind okay then I stagger over to the
bathroom and I look in the mirror um and
I see this body uh uh called Mark alms
and I say uh there is further evidence
that I still exist thank God uh now
please note both of those things I'm
calling them Mark salms u in other words
these are two um two phenomenal uh two
appearances two observational
perspectives upon one and the same thing
so there is the subjective being of Mark
PMS that I experience mentally when I
wake up before I open my eyes and then
there is the objective bodily uh thing
called Mark salms that I experience
visually uh when I look at him in the
mirror that's the dual aspect monus says
these are not two different things not
two different uh ontological entities
there's one underlying ontological
entity uh and that's called Mark salms
so then the question is which is an
abstraction then then the question
becomes well what stuff is Mark SS made
of and I'm saying Mark SS is made of a
functional mechanism uh and which the
one I was describing earlier uh is a
self-organizing therefore in biological
terms a homeostatic system uh
homeostasis is a mechanism it's an
abstraction there's there's there's we
infer the underlying mechanisms uh from
the the The observed data uh when it
comes to the the apparatus of the Mind
the thing that we are talking about here
which is also the apparatus of the brain
it's that apparatus that we're talking
about it's the it's the the functional
principles governing this part of nature
that we infer from the two observables
so when it comes to um for example
memory you know you can have a memory
that's the experience of a memory or you
can see optogenetically the neurons that
are uh activated uh whilst you are
having that same memory these are two
perspectives upon one thing which is an
abstraction called the memory system or
the function of memory so uh I think
that that is the actual thing that we're
studying in cognitive Neuroscience um
although I don't like to call it
cognitive Neuroscience because that
seems to exclude affec of Neuroscience
so the thing the thing that we're
studying in what we're let's call it
neuros pychology which is a slightly
less prejudiced word um in this in this
mind and brain science I think that the
the um the the ultimate object of study
of neuros pychology is things like the
memory system uh the perceptual system U
the executive system and so on we're
trying to discern the laws uh the
underlying monistic laws uh governing
this part of nature that we can observe
from these two different uh perspectives
both both the objective and the
subjective one now um sorry if I if I'm
getting quite abstract no no no to come
back very useful to come back to the
essential Point um if that is the
framework uh the metaphysical framework
within which I'm working and we all have
to when it comes to the Mind Body
relation uh we have to adopt a
metaphysical uh framework and and it's
good that we are clear about which one
we're adopting that's the one I'm
adopting within that framework it
doesn't make any sense to say how did
the physiological phenomenon cause the
psychological phenomenon they are those
two phenomena are dual manifestations of
a single underlying cause that
underlying cause is the mechanism that I
spoke of earlier which explains them
both um the free energy principle is is
is is such a such a thing it it's a it's
a it's a a principle which governs uh
both how we feel and what brain arousal
mechanisms uh we observe physiologically
in other words what you see with your
eyes and what you feel with your
feelings uh are are both manifestations
of that single underlying mechanism so
to say how does the brain process cause
uh the feeling uh is to ask the wrong
question uh it's to ask a question that
assumes a metaphysical relationship
which I think uh is is is the wrong
assumption it's like saying if I look um
with my eyes I see a flash of lightning
um if I listen with my ears uh I hear a
clap of Thunder uh and I ask the
question how does that visual thing uh
the flash of lightning cause that
auditory thing the clap of Thunder it's
to misunderstand that they're actually
both caused uh by a a Geo electrical
event uh which we describe abstractly
using the the the laws of physics uh
using the language of physics or or or
or or um ultimate forces you know that
that that kind of language it's not
something that you observe it's the
mechanism that you the thing that you
infer that underlies it so um when
you're saying you're wanting to know how
I'm saying I have answered you how when
I describ to you what the mechanism is
uh and I very important importantly I
need to make this clear the mechanism I
describ to you the mechanism of feeling
that is um which is which which you can
observe from two observational
perspectives in other words you can
observe brain arousal processes uh and
you can observe subjectively feelings uh
that these are both manifestations of a
single mechanism that's the one that I
described to you and this is the
important top I said very importantly it
also explains why this mean ISM has two
um perceptual surfaces why why it has
two perceptual perspectives it explains
why such a mechanism has a subjective
perspective because not everything
everything geometrically has a has a
subjective perspective in other words
you can say there is there is such a
thing uh as uh the perspective of being
a cup or being a table but that doesn't
mean that there is something it is like
to be a cup or to be a table so I'm
saying the mechanism I've described um
which is which is a a mechanism which
does not uh exist does not explain the
behavior of Cups and tables um is why
there is nothing it is like to be a cup
or a table so the the the remember that
the the underlying manistic
ontological entity that we are studying
is that mechanism which which which we
can study both objectively and
subjectively and I've described why this
particular mechanism has a subjective
aspect now to come to what I understood
to be the third part of or
third aspect of your question um which
is a sort of an evolutionary question
you're saying uh why did this happen
What functionality is added uh why what
is gained by this that that that
couldn't go on in the dark I've already
explained why I believe that mechanism
can't go on in the dark now I want to
explain what what it adds um it is in
fact I have in a way already explained
it but let me articulate it in a
slightly different way um a organism
let's say an organism because we're
talking about living things here but
there's another question as to whether
they necessarily have to be living
things but we could say a system but
let's just say a biological system an
organism um which has needs uh in other
words it has its own um biologically
viable States and it has to remain
within those States in other words it's
a an organism which functions
homeostatically um it it it needs
predictions as to how to satisfy those
needs in other words how to how to
return to homeostasis when it's
deviating from it and we are born with
such predictions us living things have
innate predictions uh those are called
reflexes those precisely are our
autonomic functions so um when I um I I
have a I have a a constant um need uh to
balance my blood gases there's a there's
a balance between oxygen and carbon
dioxide that's viable uh for a human
being and I have a very simple way of
meeting that need which is that I
breathe automatically um my my uh
intercostal muscles expand expand my
diaphragm that sucks in oxygen uh and
then uh
the the the there's the relaxing of that
of those muscles and that expels carbon
dioxide and there is actually a need
detector in your hypothalamus if you
want to describe this mechanism
anatomically which is constantly
monitoring oxygen carbon dioxide oxygen
carbon dioxide but there's one
prediction as to how to how to um how to
maintain the viable balance and that is
this autonomic breathing mechanism now
why do we ever become conscious of our
need to breathe I know you are now
becoming conscious of it because I'm
talking about it normally you're not
conscious of it um and other words what
is added by becoming conscious of it so
imagine an an organism equipped with the
with the need I've just described uh and
with the reflex of prediction the innate
prediction the fixed innate instinctual
prediction as to how to meet that need
that's fine until you place such an
organism in an unpredict environment in
other words something not predicted by
natural selection in other words not the
default environment for which this
prediction um is an appropriate one the
one that you should just breathe at a
regular rate in other words for example
what happens if you're in a carbon
dioxide Filled Room uh you're no longer
in the usual uh default environment
you're you're in a burning building um
and the room is full of carbon dioxide
at that point you become conscious of
your need need to breathe uh this is the
why question that you're asking why uh
do you become conscious of your need to
breathe it's because now you're in a
state of uncertainty as to what to do uh
your reflex autonomic uh prediction
doesn't cut it uh so you behave
stastically you you're in a state of
distress uh you you're you you're
suffering
um Suffocation alarm um or or or
respiratory distress or air hunger it
goes by various names and why it comes
to Consciousness as a feeling is because
as you randomly go upstairs uh trying to
uh do something other than your
instinctual your normal reflex of action
it feels worse uh and so that was the
wrong decision uh it was a bad choice to
go upstairs and this and and the
organism registers it in the form of
this feeling of Suffocation is getting
worse so you change your mind uh and you
go downstairs instead and there you get
the enormous relief of feeling better
you know being able to being able to
breathe the oxygen so that that feeling
um has guided your voluntary action in
fact has has has made possible what we
call voluntary action uh it's not just
random Behavior because the the your
your existing prediction doesn't cut it
uh what you do is as I said earlier
predictive work in progress in other
words you actually feel your way through
the problem uh and and and come up with
a new prediction which you then lay down
that is the Adaptive advantage that is
what is evolutionarily um added by this
extended form of homeostasis uh in which
you don't just have some sort of Auto
automatic uh regulator of um that that
that keeps you within your viable bonds
you have in addition to those automatic
Regulators you have a further mechanism
uh which kicks in when the automatic
regulator isn't working because you're
not in the environment that it it
expects um and it it it enables you to
um to navigate that uh that novel
unpredicted uncertain environment I it's
one of the what I've just said uh one of
the reasons why I I say that that that
Consciousness is felt
uncertainty that's that's a a py way of
describing what it actually is but I
hope that I've answered your question
there by saying what it adds it adds it
adds the the the ability to survive in
unpredicted novel environments prior to
the um evolution of this um mechanism
this extended form of homeostasis this
this subjective form of Home extension
of
homeostasis the what would have happened
um is that if you have a population of
the organisms that um the hypothetical
organisms I'm talking about they all uh
have this stereotyped fixed prediction
as to what to do if they find themselves
in a novel situation because of the
innate variation in the genome some of
them will do the right thing and and
some of them will do the wrong thing in
their in their random sort of thrashing
about uh the few that do the right thing
uh will then pass on uh that uh
adaptation uh to the Next Generation in
other words the Next Generation when
they find themselves in this what was
previously a novel situation that will
not be a novel situation for the Next
Generation the the functionality that
I've described supersedes that that is
the mechanism of natural selection
whereby over Generations um the
predictions are improved by natural
selection uh the the the functionality
I've disc described enables the organism
within its own lifetime uh to improve
its predictive model um in in um in
radically uncertain
circumstances and thereby to survive and
reproduce there's a lot there um so I
want to start by being philosophically
skeptical and therefore annoying and say
that I still think that this is rest on
an axiom that for example Consciousness
is there for
unpredictability because I still can't
see why in principle natural selection
couldn't have endowed us with just a
very good monitor of what to do in
uncertain circumstances so I for I can't
imagine why a zombie a philosophical
zombie wouldn't be able to recognize as
I go up the stairs there's more smoke
it's getting worse oh let me go
downstairs right and this is just you
can just keep fleshing out and having
recursive iterations on the mechanism
before it needs to come on and become
online that is and so the way that I
thought about it just to sort of put my
cards on the table because I've been
acting cryptic is I wonder whether um I
wonder whether Consciousness acts as a
coar grained representation that allows
for Speed and manageable data compress
and and and in and genders manageable
data compression such that we
cannot we can't in
principle attend to every single data um
sources out there in the world but what
Consciousness allows us to do is to
compress the data that is in the world
into something one that's prioritized
and two that can be acted upon in a fast
manner whether this is in predictable or
unpredictable circumstances and often it
will need to be done in unpredictable
circumstances but the pure notion that
Consciousness is unpredictable is is
there for unpredictable circumstances I
don't think can skirt the problem or the
contention
that hypothetic we can never run the
counterfactual but there is a there is a
hypothetical counterfactual where all of
this is being done offline you just have
a very adaptive sensor in the
hypothalamus let's say who doesn't who
who doesn't need an online self model to
recognize any signal in some phenomenal
way so that's that again I don't feel we
to go down this Rabbit Hole um well well
because you have articulated your view I
will just say something very briefly
about it which is that that is in in in
in essence and I'm I'm sorry to be so
reductionist about you the subtleties in
what you've just said but it is in
essence a attentional mechanism that
you've described it is and uh I'm saying
that's fine I spoke earlier about
prioritization so that's that's built
into what I'm saying uh but uh it's not
just any old attentional mechanism it's
attention to my homeostatic state in
other words to my deviation from my
viable bounds it's not attention to
anything in the world in other words
just unpredictability I'm saying no it's
not just unpredictability it's
unpredictability as to how to satisfy
this need in other words it's a certain
kind of unpredictability for a certain
kind of system I think that that is the
ground zero of feeling that is how it
comes into existence so it is by the
mechanism you describe but only applied
to a particular part of Nature and not
not to everything in the universe that's
a that's a very useful ad I've actually
just written this paper uh with the help
of Carl and L Costa about sort of
eliding the endogenous exogenous
attention distinction within active
inference by saying that attention is
basically as as we've been speaking
about a priority filter but always for
the sense making all organism um and and
and in active inference you can say well
and then you flesh that out and say well
the deepest most precise preferences are
encoded at the deepest level of the
generative hierarchy hence why I don't
care where my phone is when I'm
suffocating for example because the
preference I have my phone is far less
precise and far higher than um that is
exactly how I see it yep yeah okay so so
I wanted to ask you said something about
so we have dual aspect monism that we
can describe to phenomena we can take
two perspectives on a phenomena like
memory for example we can think of the
hippocampus and we can also think of
what it is like to have a memory and you
said that what the real Target of
cognitive Neuroscience or neuros
pychology should be is the single
mechanism that underlies both of those
perspectives and you preferred the
active inference or the free energy
principle might be one of those
mechanisms I wonder whether this was
relating to what people talk about in
ter in Act of inference as a dual
information geometry and what that is is
for the audience and I spoke to Van Visa
about this actually yesterday so the
podcast should be out before this one so
people can go there but the idea is that
we have an intrinsic geometry which
looks at how the actual internal states
of the markof blanket evolve over time
and then we have the E extrinsic
geometry which is what how they are uh
manifesting variational beliefs about
the external States and one is kind one
you can kind of view as if you wanted to
take a metaphysical stance or a
phenomenal stance one is the view from
within and one is the view from without
I wonder whether that Jewel aspect fits
quite nicely onto your jeel aspect
monism or whether you thought about that
yes um what you're saying intuitively
appeals to me
uh when you say I thought about it now
for precisely 10 seconds and it
intuitively appeals to me there's a
paper called um movian monism which is
by Van visa and car so that that's where
this is yes um I I just wonder you know
I I spoke to Van about this yesterday
and I said what were the metaphysical
consequences before we move on May I
just say there's something about uh the
there's something about because now I'm
remembering that paper um and and I'm
remembering what I thought when I read
it I think that there is something
special about um precision optimization
in relation to what you're talking about
um in that the Precision um assigned to
uh the incoming error signal um in
relation to the outgoing prediction um
is assed by the system uh to those to
those um to that message passing as it
were so I think that um there's there's
a special place um for precision
optimization uh in in in the story that
you just described there yeah absolutely
yeah I mean in terms of the paper that I
just wrote that's exactly it in terms of
a more like in terms of a technical Bas
graft pomdp schema what we're saying
here is sort of higher order preferences
govern Precision weighting over What's
called the likelihood Matrix the a
matrix and that's kind of been you know
Felman and Frist and then later papers
have proposed that that really is what
attention is it's optimizing that
Precision waiting yes we not yeah no
go only to add that I think a really
critical point that I really wanted to
stress in that paper is that that's not
just Precision per se so Precision I
take to be a very strict mathematical
construct in uh inverse entropy or
inverse covariance whatever you want to
say but not all signals which are given
a gain you know extra gain synaptic gain
or given attention are only those which
are precise I.E which have a clear cause
rather we we govern our attention is
governed fundamentally by our goals even
if that the object of attention isn't
necessarily precise right it can be very
ambiguous but it's very important I pay
attention to whether my garden hose is a
garden hose or a snake and that will
also be affected for whether I'm in
London or whether I'm in Sydney so just
to add that I think people it's really
important to distinguish attention
precision and precision waiting as free
individual constructs yes that makes
good sense to me um so I uh I I I'll put
it in the in in more sort of everyday
terms that that um uh it has to do
because remember I was saying it's a
particular type of system and that's
another way of saying what you're saying
that um if things with respect to the
Precision over my policies if things are
turning out as expected that's good if
uncertainty prevails that's bad and uh
so you know this is why it is good to
have confidence in your in your
policies because it will result in good
feelings is absolutely go ahead no but I
gathered that you wanted to move on to
to another topic well yeah I mean
actually just in reference I I like
making sure that people know I kind of
feel like I should let people know where
they can go to read all this stuff so
just in terms of the Precision over your
policies this is known as the gamma
parameter in active inference and if
people want to read about that Casper
hesp 21 2021 paper is a really good
place to start um where he talks about
veilance in terms of this gamma
Precision okay yes I so I um I watched
your two conversations with Lisa Felman
Barrett and greatly enjoyed them uh and
and yeah I thought they were really
fascinating and the Very novel way of
doing scientific discussion because
normally it's very angry and on Twitter
um I thought a really interesting thing
that came up although it was only really
briefly touched upon was kind of the
distinction between interception and
extra
reception and I I found actually I've
never really thought that it could
potentially be quite a blurry line but I
feel like Lisa was Keen to say that some
of the things that you were proposing
were fundamentally extra receptive I a
pin prick or something like that could
also be construed as inter receptive so
if we say okay let's take the pin prick
example and let's talk about aect so
you're not I if I'm say if I'm correct
you wouldn't believe that all affect is
fundamentally interceptive is that a
fair play fair thing to say oh yes I
absolutely disagree with that view but
slightly comically in relation to the
discussion with Lisa felin Barrett that
you're referring to that was the
starting point of that discussion was
that I said I disagree with her and Neil
Seth uh in their in their associating
affect with interception for them
interception is affect and interception
is this other form of perception
remember to them aect is just a modality
of perception it's an interceptive
modality of perception and I was saying
no I don't agree with that at all I
don't think that it is and then I used
the example of pain and I said what
could be more extra receptive you know
than this thing is from the outside
being stuck into my finger um or a
fright you know there's something
happens out there in the world and that
thing out there in the world startles me
so it's
exteroceptive and so I was saying affect
uh clearly is not extra receptive then
she got into these gymnastics that
you're referring to of saying well you
know if you do this then a pinprick is
interceptive and I say well fine you
know if you do this then that's fine but
to me the crucial thing is that that
it's neither the
extracephalic the feeling uh is the
homeostatic deviation homeostats are not
they are not interceptive or EXT
receptive they both they are registering
a a configuration um which it uh which
it infers this uh this is bad for me or
this is good for me in relation to the
particular category of need that we're
talking about so so I don't think you
and Lisa would necessarily disagree on
that if I listen to that conversation
correctly because I think she was keen
and I guess it's a fundamental part of
her theory that there isn't there isn't
necessarily meaning in the data signal
itself and it's only in its uh collision
with the prediction that we get in
basian terms a posterior which relates
to our actual fundamental prior and that
Divergence is what you might call a so I
you wouldn't disagree on
that can can I just make clear there
because you know these disagreements
with Lisa I think are very important uh
for the future of our field by which I
mean by I mean affective science that
that's the field I'm talking about
that's that what I share with Lisa is an
interest in the in the fundamental
nature of affect or what she calls
emotion because as you said at the
beginning affect and emotion and and and
so on these words are used differently
by different people for her a does not
have quality it has veillance and
arousal but it is not
distinguish in in its
intrinsic um so um the you're quite
right in everything you just said there
that she and I don't differ in the
things that you just said there but for
me the crucial point and you can see in
relation to everything that I've said to
you already why it's crucial uh is that
I think that the starting point is that
those homeostats are innate you know
that we are born with categorically
distinct
homeostats um and the I won't repeat
everything I said earlier but it is from
those homeostats uh that the uh
ultimately that the that that the
quality of feeling arises when I was
saying thirst feels different from
hunger and so on and remember I'm saying
these are not only inceptive the Fright
feels different from Pain these are
extracephalic side it's
extracephalic
from this category of need and if you
prioritize that deviation in other words
this is the one that I'm going to
now I'm going to my un this is the most
Salient category of need uh this is the
one where my I'm going to palpate my
uncertainty as I act in the world uh
this is in other words the one that I'm
going to that is now going to govern my
voluntary behavior that the quality of
the feeling uh that governs uh that
action cycle um is going to arise from
the category uh of need that we're
talking about in other words from the
homeostat
her view is that there are no innate
categories of emotion and I've just
explained why I don't agree with that
that I think is the fundamental
difference between her and me and that's
what I felt was that's what I felt was
the fundamental difference and just so I
can get clarity for myself is your view
that there is a strict mapping at least
numerically between the number of
homeostats and the number of basic
categories so is there a homat for well
these are the ANP and basic emotion you
know is there a homeostat for uh seeking
is there a homeostat for Rage or lust or
whatever I do believe that there's a a
homeostat for each one of those what he
calls basic emotions um but I need to
make clear that those what he calls
basic emotions um are not the uh sum
total of the basic homeostatic need
mechanisms uh that are at work in the in
the human or or mamalian or for that
matter vertebrate organism um the the
the um many of the things that we spoke
about at the beginning of our
conversation things like hunger and
thirst and um and um um
respiratory feelings and so on these uh
are not emotions these are at least they
don't feature in Pip's taxonomy of the
emotions because for him emotions are
not these things he calls them bodily
affects so there are many U homeostats
not seven there are many many many many
many homeostats in the human organism
and it's a very telling fact that not
all of them give rise to feelings like
blood pressure regulation for example
there's no feeling of you know how well
or badly you're doing in terms of um in
terms of um regulating your blood
pressure um and and and I'm just using
one example there are many such examples
there there ones which are transitional
which are Norm nor run autonomically and
sometimes we feel them and I just gave
an example of that when I spoke about
respiration that normally it's it's it's
handled autonomically but then at under
certain circumstances it comes to
Consciousness so I'm sorry I'm probably
being overly pedantic but the my point
is yes I do agree with you that there
for for each need there's a homeostat
but there more than seven of them many
many many more than seven of them and um
only some of them ever come to
Consciousness and only some of them
might be called emotions in my way of
using the word emotion but here's the
further very important Point um the fact
that they are categorical needs doesn't
mean that they aren't amalgams of them
uh it doesn't mean that they also aren't
higher order metacognitive um uh uh um
amalgams and elaborations and so on
for her for for Lisa that's the starting
point the starting point is that there
are these learned categories that we
then um that we then there are what she
calls emotion Concepts which we then
apply to um to what we experience
perceptually and I'm saying yeah of
course there are these learned Concepts
um but they start with uh innate
Concepts those are those are the um
those are the the the homeostats that
I'm talking about how we come to
regulate through Al
estasis and and and and learning um all
of these different mechanisms and and
orchestrate them all with each other and
so on especially us human beings with
all of these higher order abstract
Concepts that we use to do so um it
includes everything that she writes
about I think that what she writes about
describes something that definitely does
happen but I I just I I just question uh
the um the assumption that there are no
innate categories to begin with it just
makes no evolutionary sense and makes no
physiological sense it just doesn't map
on to what we know about how the brain
works um that that's the that's the
point I wanted to make yes that was the
that was the big sticking point um and
there was this kind of back and forth
about what evidence is uh which we don't
we don't necessarily need to go into but
people can watch it and I thought was
very interesting yeah well when when if
if you do if you dear listener or viewer
do watch it I want you to to to notice
one thing which I thought was was was
especially important um it's that
because Lisa's starting point is that
this idea that there are particular
circuits for particular emotions and so
on which which U of course can be
paraded and can be caricatured and can
be made to look like an idiotic local I
Iz aist stupid idea but but when she
says there are no such systems there are
in no innate brain systems for innate
emotions and and and other uh categories
of organism organismic me when she says
that please note in this conversation
with me uh I leared that she says the
same of um Vision as opposed to sematic
sensation as opposed to all faction she
says the these two are not innate
systems so if that's what she means if
if her if her uh um uh way of
understanding what we mean by an innate
system uh her way of of of using that
terminology excludes um the usefulness
of speaking about a visual system which
we all have and an auditory system that
we all have and so on I think you need
to understand that it's in that way that
she's questioning whether there are
basic emotional systems in the brain uh
if if if it's such a radical claim that
she's that she's making that um we
should not speak of any innate systems
uh of the kind that we do when we speak
of a visual auditory or C sensory and so
on system if if if if if emotion is
being lumped in with that claim then
it's not a claim only about emotion it's
a whole different way of thinking
thinking about what are useful Concepts
um and her reasoning for saying there's
no innate visual system is that if
you're blind your visual system will be
um you know will serve different
functions not innately visual well of
course if you're blind it's going to go
in an anomalous is going to organize in
an anomalous way but that doesn't mean
that it's not useful in biology to speak
of the the fact that in the normal state
of things there is an an innate visual
system but yes I wonder whether I could
you know Lisa's not here to State her
piece and so people should go and listen
and I'd love to have her on um I'm
wondering whether I can sort of Steal
man and well actually not steal man
either yourself or her but also
potentially you know offer a middle
suggestion which is could we perhaps
propose rather than well I wonder
whether Lisa would say she might
disagree that there are innate Concepts
would she disagree that there are innate
processes and by that I mean I can take
a s of active inference biological
active inference stance on this that
there are functions and anatomical
systems in the body and brain which have
priors to self-organized in a certain
way and this is the work of Mike Levin
and France cookling and this kind of
work about moros space and how that
fleshes out and so I wonder whether
because I personally and I think this is
an argument that goes all the way back
to Jerry Fodor and the debates around
Chomsky and and innate language I can't
see how for example fear would even get
ever get off the ground with no innate
priming for fear right like I agree fear
then becomes socially
modulated but how would that
categorization like I don't think Lisa
would deny that for you and I as fully
fleshed conscious propositionally using
L language users we can think about fear
and have it as a concrete object but how
that ever gets off the ground in terms
of what makes something fear what make
something first without some uh
something guiding that process whether
it's just a singular concept that acts
as a template which things get fit
fitted into or
process uh like let's say an innate
inductive in process something like that
as way that someone like Fodor might
talk about it and arguably where Chomsky
has ended up in in merge and things like
this uh maybe that would give us the
inductive background from which we can
slot these emotions into different
categories and in many ways I mean this
is this is kind of go you know it takes
us all the way to something like a
connectionist network which is that
these connectionist networks are not
completely unsupervised in the sense
that they do have prior weights um and
so yes I do think the radical
tabularasa well one I one I guess I'd
have to ask her because again I don't
want to speak on her behalf but I wonder
whether in steel Manning her position
she might have space for something like
an innate mechanism or innate process
yeah well you're right that um our
viewers or listeners must go and watch
those they they're on um I think they're
on
YouTube they are discussions I had on
her Channel yes um and um you so you
must watch it yourself and and form you
know your let and let her listen to her
speaking for herself and and form your
own opinion but um the topic that you've
just mentioned did come up um not very
uh um not very it wasn't discussed at
Great length but it came up periodically
in our two our two uh
conversations and uh my understanding
what she said is yes she certainly
agrees that there are these innate
mechanisms uh and they are instinctual
behaviors or reflexive action U not
necessarily only external behaviors but
also internal actions of within the body
um but um all that's innate is those
stereotyped uh actions um she doesn't
think or or or believe uh that there is
a feeling that goes with them um so my
my given everything that I said earlier
you can see why I think that some of
them have feeling attached to them
because that's precisely what makes you
know I am you know suffocating as
opposed to I am sleepy uh and uh and you
you act accordingly I I think the
feeling uh attaches to the category of
need um because of what feeling does um
you can I believe um um well I don't I I
don't go into too much detail but let's
just say so I believe that the feeling
is attached to the innate category um
she accepts there are inade categories
but doesn't believe that feelings are
attached to them but here's the really
interesting point she then says so we
then learn we make inferences about
these categories so the state I am in
now which I have been in before I
recognize this state this is called fear
um and that's when fear arises fear is
the concept uh the Learned concept that
you apply to the state that you find
yourself in so the first time uh that
this um uh in my view the first time
that this action uh this
instinctual action freezing and fleeing
occurs um the the the the the feeling
that you will have is fear uh her
position seems to be the first time that
it happens nothing will occur mentally
the second time that it happens you will
recognize I've been in this situation
before I call this fear and now you
formed the concept that's her way of
saying it but the crucial thing there is
there's no place for a feeling in that
why do you have a feeling feeling you've
just categorized this state as fear um
and she says yes indeed it's exactly the
same as any other type of perception
it's perceptual inference and um to me
that leaves qualia entirely out you know
it there there's no need so I asked her
the question why then do we feel uh and
she said I don't go there that's not a
scient
question yes well again uh people should
go and watch and I will email Lisa again
I emailed her and and um I think she was
very very busy she's a very busy woman I
will I will get back in contact so I
couldn't so we're running out of times
we only about 10 minutes left but I
wanted to very briefly touch upon dreams
yes um we haven't spoken we haven't done
anything to do with the kind of earlier
work of yours as I said you know you're
very famous for discovering the forbrain
mechanisms underlying dreams in I think
the late 90s and you wrote in the well
it's I think it's the 2000 paper that
what you're what you're really drawing
into question there is this Association
of REM and dreaming so REM rapid eye
movement sleep and dreaming were natur
well were historically tied together and
you show in that paper that really
nicely there's this sort of double
dissociation that you can have dreams
without REM and REM without dreams and
you said at the very end of that paper
the biological function of dreaming
remains unknown this is at least partly
attribut attributable to the fact that
the function of dreaming and the equally
unknown function of REM sleep have been
conflated for more than 40 Years of
research future studies of these
functions should be uncoupled from one
another I was curious one have they been
uncoupled from one another and two has
that given us any perview or insight
into the function of
dreaming yes um so the double dissoc
thank you for raising this it's that was
my um I mean I spent many uh happy years
uh doing a dream research um and uh I
was very fortunate in the discoveries
that I made uh in in that area which
like most um rarely significant
discoveries happen purely by luck so it
wasn't something I was looking for so I
just want to make sure that that people
understand the double dissociation
you're talking about it's not only that
you can dream outside of REM and you can
be in the REM State without dreaming
that is a is an interesting fact but
it's a that's not a that's I think was
always recognized that the correlation
between dreaming uh and and REM sleep is
a probabilistic one um you are much more
likely to be dreaming in rem than
outside of REM um but um they they the
the thing that I found which was much
more interesting I thought is that
lesions
which destroy the part of the brain that
generates REM which is which is a
colonic system in the misop pontan mum
that people who who who have lost the
capacity to have the REM State because
that part of the brain is lesioned uh
they continue to dream so with no REM
they continue to dream and conversely
there are patients um who lose the
capacity to dream uh due to a brain
lesion elsewhere uh they continue to
have REM sleep that's the double
dissociation we're talking about
standard as well yes indeed and that
lesion the one that leads to a loss of
dreaming actually there are two lesion
sites but the interesting one uh is in
the misoc cortical misol limic dopamine
circuitry so it's a different circuit
from the the one the the one that
generates REM sleep it's a different
neurotransmitter from the one that
modulates REM sleep so so dreaming uh as
opposed to REM sleep they correlate with
each other but they're not the same
thing um and the the there's an
interesting question as to why they
should correlate with each other because
they do very highly correlate with each
other but you can totally dissociate
them from each other in the way that
I've just described now um I I said
which is the quotation you just read
that we don't know what the function of
dreaming is partly because we conflated
it with REM sleep so the research that
we were doing for decades um into what
is dreaming for the the the causal
research that we did the the variable
that we manipulated was REM sleep so you
know it's not surprising that we never
got to the answer because we were
manipulating something that correlates
with dreaming but isn't actually the
mechanism of dreaming so I said at that
point in the paper that you're quoting
that now that we can see that they're
two separate mechanisms now we can
research the mechanism and function of
Dreaming by looking at the at at that
mechanism not this one um and so uh that
was bound to lead to progress um so the
the a very interesting you said so has
progress been made a lot of progress has
been made and in fact um when I said I
spent many happy years in a sleep lab I
in fact still am doing some research in
that area and so there's one study
that's still ongoing uh that um that
I've got only the I've only completed
the pilot study for it but we're now
doing the main study but the findings
were so dramatic uh in the in the pilot
study that I feel able to say a thing or
two about them
um the but it's not really in the active
inference framework so I don't don't
worry no no no no no go go go please can
be linked and you know Carl and and
Hobson uh um Carl friston and Alan
Hobson wrote some very interesting
papers within the active inference
framework about about dreaming um but
the the first thing to say is that uh
the this misoc cortical misol liic
dopamine system which clearly is the the
the driving mechan the causal mechanism
of dreaming and there's all sorts of
every method we've thrown at it you know
single cell
recordings uh microdialysis um
pharmacological probes lesion studies
positron emission tomography everything
everything points to that system that
system that system that's the one that
causes the dream state um the the the
really interesting thing about it um is
that it is it's been called uh by pank
who you men mentioned earlier the
seeking system you know the the inal
behavior that attaches to this system is
foraging exploratory interest and
curiosity U it's it it it it drives the
most sort of intense exploratory
foraging behaviors that an animal is
capable of and when you look at the
dreaming brain for example bosron
emission tomography it's really quite
astonishing to see this system is lit up
like a Christmas tree but you're asleep
you know it's like what the hell how can
how can this how can this creature be
asleep or this person be asleep if if
you weren't told that they were asleep
and you just looked at that at that um
at that brain image you would say this
person's um you know Manic and high on
cocaine or something you know so that's
the first thing that's that I think is
really interesting uh is that uh the the
the mechanism that drives the dream uh
is a is an intensely motivated active
State um and so the the the the the
first step toward a an understanding of
why do we dream uh has to be you have to
start there you know why do we have
these intense activated motivated States
while we're sleeping and secondly why
don't we wake up uh when we have them um
so um one way of thinking uh is that the
dream happens instead of real Behavior
you have you have a virtual reality in
which you are um in which you are
imagining or deluding yourself uh that
you are acting on your motivated States
why these motivated states have to
happen while you're asleep is another
question but the fact that they do
happen is is is obvious physiologically
demonstrably true so uh the the this
state is acted on in the virtual
hallucinatory reality of the dream
rather than in real reality because
um to act on them in in reality would be
incompatible with the state of sleep so
that is a that is I think a a very
simple and reasonable uh hypothesis as
to why do we dream we dream so that we
can stay asleep during this highly
motivated state of mind that occurs
State of Mind and Body the if if it
weren't for the fact that we're
paralyzed we would be running around
like lunatics so you you don't run
around like a lunatic you because you're
running around in your dream you you so
how do you test that hypothesis I said
earlier that there are two lesion sites
which lead to sensation of dreaming uh
and we've spoken only about the one the
other one is damage to the visual uh
Visos spatial cortices uh at the back of
the brain uh if you can't generate the
me the mental image the heteromodal and
predominantly visual but not only visual
imagery um that is the dream then how
can you dream so
they're theoretically less interesting
those patients they stop dreaming due to
occipitoparietal
Strokes um but if the prediction that
I've just made the hypothesis I've just
formulated as to what the function of
dreaming is if it were correct then
these patients who can't generate the
hallucinated reality because they
because of those those lesions they
should wake up they should have very bad
sleep when when this arousal State
occurs it should wake them up so that's
the prediction that I tested in my pilot
study and let me tell you I have never
seen worse polysomnograph than in these
patient wow yeah so I think we're on to
something there that what what dreams do
is they enable you to stay asleep by
by letting of steam letting of
motivational steam in a in an
hallucinatory World rather than the real
world I'm not saying that's the function
but that's a function that's very cool
that's very cool people have to keep
their eyes out for that for those sets
of papers mark this was awesome we
covered so much ground uh I'm I'm really
really very grateful indeed I always
like to ask people just to say at the
very end where people can find them if
they have you know if people have
questions or people want to read your
work how can people reach out to you or
where should they find your work so uh
to contact me you can contact me by
email um it's just my name Mark somms at
UCT University of Cape Town doac
academic. Za which is South Africa so
mark. somms u.c. Za I am also for my
sins on what used to be called Twitter
but it's now called something else that
I don't want to say um so there there
I'm markor SS at Mark
and we'll make sure to put your Google
Scholar and website and all this stuff
on in the video description again mark
thank you so so very much I enjoyed it
thank you all right